I'm part of a machine that always wins.
There's no worse enemy than the United
States Marine. Um,
you know, we're we're masters of
controlled chaos and violence.
You know, there were some definitely
scary parts of that
marginal is such a difficult piece of
ground. Hundreds and hundreds of Taliban
here and not only Taliban but kind of
the hardcore extremist best trained guys
that got IEDs everywhere. Triple
possible, you know, anti-aircraft guns.
Definitely expecting casualties,
but that's what the Marines do. Whatever
the president needs us to do is what we
do.
What's going on, Bravo?
>> You guys ready to go?
>> The Taliban have their fist in the mix
here. Trust me, this is going to be
chaotic. This plan that we've rock
drilled over and over. As soon as you
get off the bird, it's not worth
anything.
Every single one of you is going to have
to make a hundred decisions that there
is no right answer to. But guess what?
You have to act. You have to decide. You
have to act. I've talked to you before
about the gift of aggression. You're
here for a reason. When the enemy
chooses to face us on the battlefield,
win the direct firefight right now.
Overwhelming surgical firepower. Destroy
him immediately.
I guarantee you we will lose Marines. I
guarantee you what we will. Don't let
emotions control you. There's 80,000
civilians in this city.
There's maybe a thousand enemy when I go
home. I don't want to feel ashamed
because, you know, I'm I'm having
problems sleeping at night because I'm
not sure that I did the right thing.
What happens over the next five days
will be a cornerstone of your memory for
the rest of your life.
All right, Jen. That's all I got.
>> [music]
>> in Afghanistan. The stage [music] is set
for one of the biggest Allied offensives
so far. US Marines are heading up a
force to attack the Taliban.
>> They are gathering around the town of
Marjah in Helman province, getting ready
to drive off the Taliban and restore
government order.
This is the first major offensive since
President Barack Obama announced he was
sending 30,000 reinforcements, a new
strategy for turning back the Taliban.
>> Afghanistan is not lost, but for several
years it has moved backwards. Gradually,
the Taliban has [music] begun to control
additional swas of territory.
>> This is a day with destiny. For the rest
of your careers, you will be known as
Marian Marines.
>> The Afghan army who will be fighting
alongside the Marines.
>> You don't want to mess with this guy.
I'll tell you that.
>> We will pursue a military strategy that
will secure key population centers.
>> The Marines have effectively cut off all
escape routes out of Mara. They're doing
everything they can to let the people of
Margin know they're coming. Many
families have already left the city to
avoid being caught in the crossfire.
>> Ultimately, our efforts across
Afghanistan are about changing the
perceptions of people.
>> I want the Afghan people to understand
America seeks an end to this era of war
[music] and suffering.
>> Is considered a key test of Obama's
strategy.
This is a critical point.
It may be the critical point.
>> God bless you and God bless the United
States of America.
>> Thank you very much.
>> Thank you.
>> Reports from inside the city suggest
that hundreds of hardcore insurgents are
bracing for a fight.
What else?
Right now we're sweeping some IEDs,
hoping we don't step on anything. It's a
very slow process and with this many
guys could take a while and that's what
these IEDs do. They take us away from
our own game plan.
So we're having to swap up our tactics
and
kind of play uh the chess game. It's not
checkers now.
You see all those antenna?
That's building 21.
They're going this way.
>> That's three. Three in about the last 10
minutes.
Just keep in mind there's a couple guys
at this intersection. They're walking
down that road. It looks like they
definitely know we're here now. They're
just walking around watching us like
we're the zoo trying to maneuver all
around us.
Comfortable situation. I know a lot of
them have left the city, but
I'm sure several stayed.
As they pop up, start firing.
Lay into them.
>> Push up and try to get eyes on this
first compound right there. All right.
Let's go. Come on,
>> Smith. Watch your flame.
Who's right there?
>> Get over here.
>> Shoot his ass.
Oh [__]
>> Oh [__]
>> Come here. Come here. Come here. Get
down. Where you hit at? My [__] leg.
>> Oh [__]
>> What the [__]
[applause]
>> I got you, boy. I got you. I got you.
>> Roger. This is 31. It's Doc Morrison.
Right leg.
>> Arterial bleed. Heavy red blood.
>> Where's that coming from?
>> What do you see?
What do you see?
>> Started firing from that compound over
there.
>> There's like eight of them. Shot the
rockets.
>> Let it roller
>> and I'm They were effective. Like no
[__] Like I was Yeah, I'm It's
effective. Let's [__] get the [__]
away.
>> Took fire from down here at this
intersection. If they fired that RPG, it
popped around that corner from that
intersection, fired the RPG.
>> There was no pangs or claps. It was all
>> singing.
I need to get down, brother. We're
taking fire. [__] goddamn [__]
>> Have we stopped bleeding yet?
>> Stop for a couple minutes now.
>> I got to get you out of here, man. So,
>> we'll get him [__] moving.
>> We need air on that [__] right
there.
>> It's pretty close.
>> Yes. Every time they that moped stopped
at the end, he was dropping guys off and
they ran in there. That's where they are
flooded. There's at least 10 to 12.
>> Get a [__] shot. the next one you
[__] see. Do you hear me?
>> Son of a [__]
>> What? He's getting closer.
>> Why not call in there now?
>> They may be trying to, but
uh they're just worried about collateral
damage and uh affecting the people,
which you don't want to take out
innocent people, but what's more
important, your Marines or
guy shooting at you?
the Taliban fighters are doing that
probably
that leg across across.
>> Yeah, I'm worried about you getting
infection in that [__] sore, dude.
>> Here,
keep it out of the water.
>> Jump over there. Go.
>> Get up there.
>> Get up there
to the top. Hold fast.
>> Hurry up.
>> Alto together. I've seen about 40
>> using really good tactics. They've been
uh [__] hiding AK-47 one spot and
moving to another. Then when they finish
that spot, they run to another spot
that's actually good, good hidden place,
have the AK-47 there, and they shoot off
the grounds until it's a over there, and
they move again. Do the same thing over
again. It's not just one guy spraying
>> like uh we're used to. These guys
actually know what they're doing.
Hey, there's women and children in the
building. We're each other in the
building. Weapons tight. We're going in.
Let's go.
We need a [__] axe or something.
>> We got them
>> shovel.
>> Let's get it. Let's get holes in these
holes. 240 up there.
>> Roger. We're taking contact from
building 30. Break.
>> Hey, what do they [__] ask?
Mong just trees blocking
>> that that building out there is a
sporadic fire coming from
>> [__] good eyes on this [__]
right here.
>> I don't like being here.
>> Huh?
>> I don't like being here
>> in this place.
>> Not at all.
It's too [__] small.
Close to a [__] attack position.
>> Perfect range for rockets and motors.
Easy [__] distance to judge.
>> So, it' be pretty easy to bracket.
>> I'm sure we won't stay here long.
>> That's where they're [__] dipping
from.
>> He was in there shooting at shots from
that crack right there.
[__] All
right, fall back in real quick.
>> All right, currently we're right here.
First is going to [__] fire a jab
into building 20. All right, that door I
ain't all about going through it because
they could [__] probably run back and
forth. Not kosher.
>> So clear 20 and 21 and [__] fire
another damn [__] into the [__]
building 19 because if they have a
[__] machine gun right here they just
kill [__] entire platoon.
God damn.
>> God damn it, bro. Can't [__] move in
this [__]
>> Cover and maneuver.
>> Tell them we're getting shot at from
behind us.
>> Yeah, exact same building.
Go go go go go go go.
>> Go, [__]
>> Jesus.
>> Holy [__]
>> Oh my god.
Dude, you got to drop bombs. Bombs don't
miss.
>> That's what I'm saying, bro. With this
gun [__]
>> They wouldn't get closer than 600 meters
last year. These guys are like 150
meters. Get closer.
>> And they're these they got effective
fire. Last year was just straight
sporadic. Never hit anything really.
>> Little boy. Miss him
>> for real, dude.
>> How old is he?
>> Five months.
>> Don't worry, guys.
>> Five months. February 13th.
>> Miss him.
>> We'll help you out, man.
>> I'll be home to him, too.
>> How much time did you spend with him
before you came in?
>> Uh, about two months. Two, three months.
>> Not too bad.
>> It'll be big when I get home. Can't
wait.
Was
that us shot?
>> What's going on?
>> What do we got? What do we got?
>> I was pissing.
>> Try to hit the medevac bird with an RPG.
They [__] missed.
>> They're shooting at the one bird. They
have the meta back on the ground over
there. And the other one I think is shot
on fire over
>> [__] man. Telling you crazy
cutters.
>> Copy taking fire from 25.
>> What's your direction to move
>> cutters?
Ready? Yeah.
>> All right, here we go.
>> [laughter]
>> [__] you suckers.
>> They're probably like, "Oh, look at our
RPGs." Imagine how that felt.
southern Afghanistan.
Operation Mushtarak meaning together.
Moving deeper into Marger.
As a way to show their joint control of
the operation, US commander Stan B.
Crystal and Afghan General Sheer
Muhammad Zazi held a press conference
together.
>> While this is an Afghan-led operation, I
think it highlights the special
partnership that we've developed that
I'm very proud of.
>> And I would ask for the media to watch
the bravery of Afghan National Security
Forces.
We will shift the emphasis of our
mission to increasing the size of Afghan
security forces so that they can
eventually take the lead in securing
their country.
>> This is not ring companies here and
Afghan companies here. This is squad and
squad, platoon and platoon going out
together. There's a brotherhood there of
great trust and cooperation between us.
And this isn't fluff. This isn't talk. I
mean, this is the real deal. Uh the the
Marines have great respect for the
Afghan army and I think that's
reciprocal.
>> All right. Thank you.
>> Next question. Excosion.
>> Get. You got to be the first one going
in to the front.
>> Right behind the metal guy.
>> There. Go up. Go up front. Go.
Hey, to the right. To the right.
>> What's up? What's up?
>> Oh,
>> Romo,
get up here. Little [__] ass. Romo,
kick the door in and move out the way.
And they're going to go in. Okay.
>> Yes. You kick the ball and move and
they're going to go in.
>> As soon as they kick kicks the door,
>> go in as soon as he kicks the door.
>> Go.
>> Get the [__] in there.
>> No. [__]
>> Damn it.
>> Get the [__] in there.
>> Watch the corners. Watch the corners.
>> Go, go, go, go, go.
>> Let's go. Come on. Let's go.
>> Hey, let's go. Get in there.
>> Look. Come here. too many of us.
>> Kick that [__]
>> You can probably bring it in.
>> Roger.
>> It's locked.
>> No. No. No.
>> Get in there. Get in there. Is it clear?
>> Good.
>> Good. Good.
>> No. Good.
>> Good. Good. No one in there.
>> No. Talib.
No.
>> No. Okay.
>> Yes, sir. Here
was a police station but
>> you tell some other people moved in.
>> Taliban Taliban.
>> Taliban.
>> Taliban. Taliban.
>> That's opium. the opium ball
which is then processed into [laughter]
that. This is about $60,000 US.
This is ammonium nitrate to make
ammonium nitrate aluminum which is known
as anal. It's IED making material.
It's my understanding Alpha and Charlie
got minimal contact.
>> I mean, they've got sporadic stuff, but
it sounds like everybody, all the
fighters are kind of stuck in the center
of town. There's about 250 of them left.
It seems like they're all right here.
>> We're the only show in town from what I
understand.
So, we flew in, met some pretty
significant resistance right up front.
Um, after we landed within a couple
hours, we were attacked from 360° while
we continue to push up and uh seize our
little foothold of uh the crew village
here.
We lost an engineer that was trying to
bring up breaching equipment, you know,
and I'm the one that called back and
told him, "Get the apods. Bring it up
here." And somebody, you know, I can't
remember who it was. Somebody's arguing
with me on the radio about how heavy the
fire was. And I told him, "I don't care.
Get the apods up here. We got to get
into the objective."
And about half hour after the incident,
I found out that doing that, you know,
one of uh one of the Marines had been
killed and been shot, you know, in the
back as he was moving out to get that
piece of gear.
We always go into these fights. We know,
you know, in a fight like this, I know
that I'm going to lose Marines. But this
guy was doing exactly a task that I told
him we needed to do. And uh, you know,
he got killed doing it. So, that's uh
that was definitely the lowest point
I've had so far.
That that took me a while to reconcile
in my head.
And we move on now to Afghanistan and
the massive battle to clear the Taliban
stronghold of Maria.
>> Pentagon spokesman Jeff Morurell says
the Taliban is being squeezed. Our hope
is clearly that this is creating a a
certain amount of discontent, worry,
turmoil within the organization such
[music] that it is
Whoa.
>> Holy [__] That's right there.
>> Hey, is it that morph talking about?
>> Hey, it's in the bizaar. It's blowing up
the bazaar.
>> Bizarre
talking about it. Roger.
>> Okay, come on.
>> So, they're hitting us short, which
means they're going to be adjusting on
us.
>> Yes.
>> Hey, keep [__] down.
>> Holy [__]
>> There's a bunch of propane tanks on
fire.
>> Look at it. The gas station's about to
[__] blow up.
>> Tupac,
>> what does he got?
>> Trying to use it to close in.
>> Maybe they're trying to close in.
were resisting and the town remained
under their control.
Better put my gear on.
>> Can't leave the building without my gear
on.
>> Or I can, but that wouldn't be very My
wife wouldn't like that.
what they're saying on the radio says uh
that they're actually trying to move
closer to the base to our defense here.
>> So,
we got to fix our post up. So, they're
probably going to see us on this roof
and start firing. So, I want to get down
as quick as possible. So, we got to roll
>> talking about
>> Yeah. needs to be right here.
>> All right. Come on. We're going We're
going to link up with third pursuit
first. All right. All we got to do is
push north.
>> Hey, pack up, Gy.
>> And they say they got one out in the
road over there. They said they could
see the line.
>> Spider drop, baby. Spider drop. Who
can't stop?
>> Show Show them the wire and stuff that
you see.
>> I don't know what they see.
>> Hey. Hey, listen up. Hey, we got there's
a [__] ID over there.
>> It's [__] It's It's huge. I don't
know what the [__] it is. It looks like
maybe a 50 lb bag or something.
>> All right. Hey.
>> Hey.
>> Could be anything in there, but it's
it's big as [__] And it's electric.
It's running into the other compound.
>> Yeah, it looks at least a 50 lb or
whatever. Whatever it could be.
>> Just keep [__] eyes on me until I get
back cuz I got to sweep down there. All
right.
>> Okay.
>> Cuz I don't want somebody popping over
with a [__] gun in the cabin. You
know what I'm saying?
I didn't get it.
>> Who the [__] he talking about?
>> Yo, get ready to move. Get ready to
move.
>> Fact behind here. Let's go
>> quickly. You only got a minute. Come
here, Mohamd. Get over here. Get down.
Get down against the wall.
>> Get low.
>> I lost.
>> Hey, listen up. After it goes off,
listen for uh Frag. All right. So,
everybody be quiet.
God damn.
>> All right, let's I just got to look down
the alley and make sure it's all [__]
gone. All right,
>> let's walk around the corner here.
>> Hey, I got two guys up there.
>> Two guys running.
>> No, they're not running. They're
walking.
>> Spot it, Haiti. See what you got.
>> They just went down behind like a
[__] little BM or some [__] You see,
>> is that shooting at us?
That sound like that sound like
>> Hey, let's go. Where's the [__]
target at?
>> What do you got?
>> Give me a goddamn shot at him.
>> Christ sakes. The [__] ones you see.
You see a guy out there, you [__] hit
him.
>> See the Brown.
>> Show it to them. Show it to them.
>> It's 12:00. 12:00.
>> Yeah,
>> they're on. One shooter on top of the
roof.
>> We spotted him. We're going to take a
long shot and knock him out. I'll copy.
>> Slow and methodical. Look at those
[__]
>> Bring the other one.
>> Give me a shot at it.
>> Hey, put your head down.
>> You ready? Go.
We got hit.
>> Did you volunteer to do this job?
>> Yes, I did.
>> Gets a little fun sometimes. A little
crazy others.
>> You see that?
>> Nothing. Nothing.
Nothing.
We're going over the wall.
>> Going over the wall. They're going into
this [__] building.
John, John, John, get the [__] over
here.
>> Get over the damn wall. Find out what
the guy's waving at.
>> You think we speak, too? Get the [__]
over here.
He called me a [__]
>> This little son of a [__]
>> Come on. Hey.
Hey, he's 20 years old.
>> Is he really 20 years old?
That's
>> freaky.
Mommy.
I stay here.
>> You stay here.
>> Yeah, it's good. He can stay here with
us.
We're going to find the Taliban.
>> Tell them we're going to find him.
>> Okay.
>> We're going to kill him. I go backed.
Wait on that break
as we're pushing up. Take a look.
It's safe to walk here.
>> More bombs out here.
>> If there any more Taliban bombs any day,
ask him
right here.
No, no, no, no.
No mind, no ID.
>> Hey, hey, let's let's go ahead.
Yes.
He is the father of these guys.
Don't
tell
stuck inside in the house.
right there.
That's
>> not sound good.
Hey, is there any way we can
tell what you want to do?
So, anything else? We would just like to
rent this place out for the night.
>> Tell the wait one. All right.
where they No, they can they'll stay
here with us. They'll be okay to stay
here with us tonight for tonight.
>> Uhhuh. Mhm.
>> This is good.
Sure.
and give me a give me a mad dash once
you get there.
>> Roger.
>> All right.
Hey, there. Yeah, they're on that side.
East side.
>> All right. It sounds like it's coming
from the building directly east of the
moss.
>> I got
from across the street.
>> Hey,
>> I'm going to pop out. You just run in
the
>> middle.
>> [__] death.
I like [laughter]
>> it's coming from back where that [__]
And that compound
>> 600 m out
>> my direct front.
>> I said 600
6 0.
>> Did they shoot the sandbag?
>> I don't think so, sir.
>> It sure looked like he shot the sandbag
to me.
>> He did.
Sniper most psychologically
>> effective weapon on the battlefield
because there's nothing you can do about
it,
>> you know.
>> Okay, sir. What do you got up there?
>> Lang Lang your DM.
>> Yeah, that's him firing.
>> Mark,
>> I wonder what direction they hear this
from.
>> [snorts]
[laughter]
>> I came up and uh I turned around to uh
get my rifle past me and as I turned
around I guess my head was just a little
above the sandbags and he shot and he
ended up hitting me directly in the head
and uh it cracked me back and I was
dazed and didn't really know what was
going on and I just told I I was like
I'm hit
but this is where it hit
about an inch above of uh my eye. And uh
this is the mount where it hit. This is
what they say stopped the round from
actually coming through
the uh Kevlar. It hurt really like
really really bad. I I thought I was
dying. I thought I' I'd actually been
hit. So it scared me pretty bad.
>> Why does Cody think it's coming? You
know,
>> you said two 300 meters from the cracks.
Bossman, stay motivated.
clear the enemy out and and let the
people return.
General Mcrist and every expert that uh
talks about counterinsurgency, you know
that we pretty clearly understand now
that the key to to winning any fight
like this is to uh control the
population and not control them, but um
I don't want to use win hearts and
minds, but that's basically it. You
know, to
get the people on your side
and let them understand that you're here
for them.
Afghans believe more of what they see
than what they hear.
>> This is a struggle for the support of
the Afghan people. Our willingness
[music] to operate in ways that minimize
casualties or damage, even when doing so
makes our task more difficult, is
essential to our credibility.
The hope for NATO trying to win support
among the locals.
>> Civilian deaths in Afghanistan have put
pressure on foreign troops trying to win
the trust and support from citizens.
>> I cannot overstate my commitment to the
importance of this concept.
You got three picks.
You guys dead
>> building number 29
>> and north 1800 me egress right poles
into the overhead advised ready for
final remarks
line 8 1,800 m northwest. That is
northwest 1,800 meters.
>> All right, we got everything we need.
>> Roger. That is confirmed. That is your
target. We are awaiting approval.
>> We're trying to get [__] clearance.
>> We're watching them for 30 minutes
progress.
Where's it? Where's six?
>> A firm hog. Hold for now. Abort for now.
>> [__]
>> Siege copy. Thanks.
>> Huh?
Gunny and I will be in the rear with all
the headquarters. Give you EOD. All
right.
>> There's a nice sturdy wall here. We'll
follow down. There's a little trench
here. Set up right here. And this is
where we were at.
>> All right. Good. I'm good, sir.
Any
[snorts] questions, Rios? You know what
your job is? How many we're bringing all
day? Leave it.
Same [__] you did last night, man.
You're fine. Leave it. Just leave it.
You're pointing at people. Leave it.
You're good.
>> Step time. Is your boys ready? Char
ready?
>> Yeah, we're ready.
>> We're stepping.
Yeah, I do.
>> Roger. Be advised,
there's mass movements around buildings
29 and5. I'll copy.
Let's go
now. Get in. Go. Go.
>> Get in.
>> Go in that building.
>> So, we need to get in there and clear
this building out.
>> Come on. Let's go.
Look. Oh dear.
Three people up here for me.
They're on the back side of that
building somewhere. Hey, keep eyes in
case they start eressing to the west.
>> There they are. There they are.
Copy. Tango.
>> Hey, get off. Get off.
>> Get down the corner.
>> Hey, they're shooting them goddamn RPGs
right [__] here, dude. Hey, 240
gunner needs to scoot up to the edge of
the wall. You're on target, but scoot
the [__] up.
>> I hit that first guy. He's [__] dead.
>> I like to hear, baby.
>> I hit that guy right in the [__]
head.
>> [__]
>> Say again.
>> That was intense.
>> Man, those [__] [__] are using
those kids and women as cover to get out
of there. Horseshit, man.
Give me a 203. Come here, Nimz. Here's
what I want you to hit. See those three
trees right there?
>> Big ones?
>> You see those big tall ones?
>> Yeah.
>> Just right on the other side of that
building. I want you to pepper them.
>> Hey, range is 300.
>> 300. All right.
Stop the cops building whipping it
through that [__] right window. You
understand?
>> That's the one that's been shooting at
us all from the park.
>> Holy [__]
>> You guys suck ass.
Solid copy. Again, we're in building
four and uh pretty sure that three took
contact from either building 10 or 11.
It was right on top of us.
>> Yeah, victory is achieved.
Hey, keep it spread out.
The eggs made it. Huh?
That's pretty impressive.
The egg survive and everything else
goes.
>> [snorts]
>> Look how look at our position from here.
>> That roof right there is where we
ambushed them.
>> That's the roof you guys were on.
>> Yep. That was behind that little
triangle thing standing up.
>> Oh yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> As you can see from here, it's a perfect
position. It totally isolates the entire
rest of the town. They had nowhere to
go. We had them completely trapped.
>> Oh, you weren't that far.
>> These [__] didn't have a chance. No.
And they had no idea we were up there.
No, they didn't.
>> No.
[snorts]
>> Huge moral victory for the company.
>> Oh my gosh.
Those
didn't work, did they? [__]
>> Six.
>> Yep.
>> Oh, yeah.
>> He died right where he was laying.
He hit his he had his hand rig rigger
mortise had set in around his around the
rifle so he was still gripping it.
>> I think it's a 8 mm mouser.
>> What are you going to do with him?
>> What him?
>> Yeah.
>> I don't believe we're going to do
anything with him.
>> We're just leave him there.
They say he was not Talib. They forced
him to give them
the Taliban forced him give them gun to
you.
This is it.
We roughly knew where he was. [snorts]
>> Perfect sniper position.
>> Look at our post.
>> Roger Coc believe we've identified the
uh sniper position break. Uh there's a
vertical loophole in the wall here.
break has perfect side alignment for the
post for Lamont when the snappers were
hit. Break
>> and we found 17 17 556 rounds.
>> How was one of your men shot from here?
>> Uh three of them actually or four three
medevacs for sure.
So, he's probably sitting back in the
room in the shadow where we couldn't see
indication of his weapon at all,
shooting through this slit in the wall.
>> Perfect angle uh to know that he has to
be far enough back so that his muzzle
flash isn't seen and uh certainly to
engage targets. You know, he was hitting
him in the chest and in the head from
back here. So, he was uh probably well
trained military.
>> Absolutely.
>> Yep.
>> What military would have would have
trained him? possibly ours at some
point. Probably using a a weapon that we
supplied him in some way or another.
>> But good to know we found a spot and we
own it now.
>> We're burning daylight. This is done.
>> All right, we're ready.
>> Yeah. All right, let's go.
>> Let's continue the game.
>> [music]
>> They're all wired in with electrical
wire daisy chained uh to uh make them
simultaneously detonate.
>> Actually the most complex one I've uh
I've found in country so far.
>> The intention was to catch a whole
platoon all of them at once in the
alleyway. Daisy tank probably uh
probably 150 m.
>> Yeah, these are probably the best
looking pieces of ordinance I've seen in
this country.
>> It's heavy metal. The deck cord goes off
and pushes everything out uh out the
front of it. Just works like a big
cannon with a bunch of crap stuffed in
it.
>> Nice.
>> It's a bit like swimming in the ocean.
You'd never do it if you knew how many
sharks there really were.
>> That's a money shot.
Bring
it out. Take cover.
would have been killed already.
>> Get in there.
Stay here. Stay here. Sit. Sit back
down.
>> Sit down.
>> Come on, [__] Back. Move on. Go back.
No.
>> Sit down. You sit down. Sit down.
>> Sit down.
No.
There you go. There you go. There you
go.
>> Yeah. There you go.
See it? It's pretty much a cylinder with
explosives and a whole bunch of nasty
frag that they stick in it. It's pretty
much pointed right at you right now.
You going to try and uh burn this one
out
>> there.
A general says US-led forces control the
roads and markets in the Taliban
stronghold.
>> A battle going well.
>> Taliban finished. Taliban go.
>> [crying]
>> do the next part is to hold the area
that we have. Once we push the enemy
out, we have to hold security here and
allow the people to start to move back
in and resume their daily lives. And
then from there we have to, you know, we
build on um,
you know, what we've established. We
help them, you know, open their schools
back up and open their bizaars back up
and establish police stations and the
local government and, um, you know,
allow the local government to start, you
know, building their projects as well.
So that, you know, in the grand scheme,
that's kind of how how counterinsurgency
works.
Gentlemen, thank you all for coming. My
name's Captain Ryan Sparks. We're very
happy. It's a great day that we can uh
you know, the Taliban are gone and we
can finally start to open your bazaar
back up, get all of your stores
repaired, fix anything that's broken so
that you can uh start your life again as
soon as possible.
>> [laughter]
>> Hey,
>> first store open, baby.
>> The Taliban will eventually lose their
freedom of movement. They'll become
irrelevant and, you know, they'll just
dissipate.
>> They'll become irrelevant. All right.
All right.
No.
>> Okay, we're going to move back to the
marketplace. Beep up the security. Copy.
>> Clear. Copy. When you get here, we'll
work through the details.
>> Have you guys seen MLAN? What's up, bro?
>> You here for this meeting? Call this?
>> Yeah. All right. You got the uh civil
affairs guy.
>> I got Gunny D.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Is he here?
>> No.
>> He's the guy who's actually handling the
payment is my understanding.
>> Want to see what you backed 11.
>> So 17 total.
>> There were 17 people in the house and
four were killed. So that's four were
killed. So that's the guy. We're going
to talk the guy back.
you're looking at the definition of
innocent people. There's no question
about it. You know, little girls. I
mean, there's there's just no
way to rationalize
um that this was in any way a good thing
or justified or it just it's just a
terrible failing, a terrible sight. Um
well
guyscheech
Forever
[snorts]
I was waiting for your call to call me
to come out and take a safe place.
I don't know what happened. Somebody
fired or something happened in my house.
by
the one family is almost finished.
There's only one child left and the
other uh family got two angels and
>> so there there were four deceased bottom
one
>> check [snorts]
>> tell them I I I'm very sorry and I can
feel his pain
>> he's going through
>> we're really sorry for uh for what
happened yesterday
>> it pains us all here to
to know what you must be going through
right now with the loss that you just
suffered.
There's not there's nothing we can do to
bring back your loss. What we can do is
try to help you out
by
by giving you uh the very least that we
can
with a payment for your losses.
So,
[clears throat]
what I'll do now is uh I'll present him
with the with the condolence payment.
[snorts]
Um, and like I said, it's it's it's the
it's the absolute least that we can do.
Um,
because obviously there's you can't
bring back someone you love.
Again,
I'm deeply deeply sorry,
>> gentlemen. This is for you for your
losses.
You know,
>> the US Marines, the the citizens of
Afghanistan and the government of
Afghanistan together can achieve great
things to make Afghanistan a safer and
more prosperous place for all.
I've been told this by Afghans before.
I don't mind Marines. I don't mind
Taliban. I just want everyone to leave
me alone and leave my I want to leave my
life, you know, and I I think there's
something to be said for that point of
view. And certainly if you've lost
family members, I'm couldn't stand in
front of you and tell you otherwise. And
that's it's not really my my place.
I I don't know if I was in his shoes.
It's almost like there's two entirely
different levels. There's the political
level and then there's the level on the
ground. Um I'm not quite sure I've
entirely reconciled them for myself
right now.
[snorts]
Yeah. Here we go.
>> [screaming]
>> foreign
[cheering]
speech.
>> [cheering]
>> So NATO has staked a lot of this
operation in MAGA. How is it defining
success?
>> This whole Margera offensive is all
about bringing governance uh as as
General Mcrista said, government in a
box. bring in what they're calling a
government in a box and show the locals
that the central Afghan government can
try to take over operations.
We need more troops, training and
assistance. And that's why we are
increasing our efforts to train Afghan
security forces.
It is slower and harder than we
anticipated.
>> I do not want to underestimate or
understate the challenge.
>> Very important test case to find out if
the new US strategy will work.
Copy.
We refurbished the whole mosque, put
their fancy minoretses up there, and you
got to see Gunny D Park,
which is what they call it. We keep
trying to change the name. They won't
let us.
>> We're trying to get it to uh Freedom
Park,
>> but they redid this whole all the walls
on the outside of this mosque.
>> Yeah. Here's the park. We're pretty
proud of this right here.
>> As you can tell, the benches are a
little slanted right there, but uh we're
working on that because these people
aren't used to benches here. So,
>> because we're trying to create a little
local economy here around the bazaar
that eventually become self-sufficient.
So, we start out with, you know, cash
for work and quick impact projects to
get the bazaar clean and to get it
functioning again. And then that injects
money into the bazaar. That's kind of
the overall
plan.
Working good so far.
He was the guy that was [__] telling
all the rest of them what to do.
>> Oh yeah.
>> Our exit strategy
This turns into the police. Then we go
to the next village, turn it into the
police, and then we go home.
>> Is he currently in good health?
>> Yes.
>> The reality is is that six months ago,
I'm sure some of these guys are Taliban.
>> Um,
>> we'll see what happens.
What's going
speech. Speech. Speech.
Holy crap.
Holy [__]
Oh my god. Barely missed.
>> Say that just barely missed. Huh?
>> That whistle pass.
definitely the most difficult tour I've
done. Um, and
you know, in order for me to do my job,
I have to have some loyalty and faith,
but
the Taliban are still here and we still
are taking casualties. You know, every
couple days or well, not every couple
days, once a week, once every two weeks.
um you know, somebody gets shot in the
arm or shot in the leg or you know,
so it's it wears on you. It wears on the
Marines.
>> These people, I don't they're not like
Americans. How
there's no way you can trust them.
They let the Taliban beat them.
But if it comes to one of us
saying the wrong phrase or anything to
these people, they just lose their lid,
you know, cuz we're Americans. And that
Taliban was from the same tribe as me,
you know, and it's ridiculous. It's a
it's a mind [__] It's frustrating. And
that that's a losing ball game.
You know, Marines don't fight wars.
Marines fight battles. Um,
and I think, you know, Marge is an is an
example of that.
You know, the war on terror or whatever
happens here, you know, in the next
months, in the next year, whatever this
place was like before we got here,
whatever impact we had here,
uh, we had our operation order and we we
fought the battle. And um
and the other stuff I think will drive
you crazy.
We are pressing forward in Afghanistan
from Mara to Kandahar.
So make no mistake, we have a clear
goal.
This is the area that we're that we
stopped trying to control out that way.
Um, it kind of our our area of control
fades a little bit as soon as you get
about a click away from here. It
gradually gets worse, but this is the
this is the edge of where we're really
actively trying to uh
secure the area. Literally right there,
that road.
This is probably one of the most hostile
places in Afghanistan. Still,
might as well be a different country.
Yep.